Guide to the Records of the International Federation for Modern Languages and Literature (FILLM) MC.176
New York University Archives
Records of the International Federation for Modern Languages and Literature (FILLM)
1959-1967
1960-1964
New York University Archives
International Federation for Modern Languages and Literatures
Baugh, Albert C. (Albert Croll), 1891-1981
MC.176
3.5 Linear Feet
The Records of the International Federation for Modern Languages and Literature (FILLM) contain a wide array of files related to the functioning of the organization and its interactions with other language associations and societies. The records are arranged alphabetically in one series and consist mainly of correspondence, meeting minutes, travel and conference information, invitations to scholars and universities, and other administrative files.
Scope and Content Note
Files in this collection date from 1959-1967 and relate to the functionings of the organization. Typed correspondence and draft letters, particularly of the general organization and of Dr. Stanley Aston, make up a large portion of the collection. Records relating to the FILLM's interactions with other language associations and societies are also present, including the Australasian University Language and Literature Association, the Association Internationale des Etudes Francaises, the Etudes Slaves, the Internationale Vereinigung Fur Germanische, and the Societe de Linguistique Romane. A variety of travel information, including budget and hotel files, records from a travel agency, and housing and tour information, is dispersed throughout the collection. Information on the FILLM's congresses and other conferences like the East-West Symposium and the meetings of the Modern Language Association are similarly included. Budgets, insurance information, invitations, fundraising materials, committee information, vitae sheets, treasurer's reports, and other records comprise the general administrative files in the collection.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically in a single series.
History of the International Federation for Modern Languages and Literature
The International Federation for Modern Languages and Literature (FILLM) was originally founded in Oslo in 1928 as the Commission Internationale d'Histoire Littéraire Moderne and subsequently reorganized in its present form in 1951 upon the formation of the United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (UNESCO). The FILLM is affiliated upwards in the UNESCO pyramid to the International Council for Philosophy and Humanistic Studies (CIPSH), one of the three UNESCO-sponsored non-governmental organizations representing the major branches of knowledge.
The FILLM is the world's ceiling organization for international language and literature associations of varying size, function, and constitution. These member associations focus on the major language subject areas and fully reflect the diversity of scholarly approaches within the field, including the many different kinds of interdisciplinary approaches. Some member associations specialize in particular theoretical or methodological approaches to language and literature, and others focus on some particular period of literary or language history, or on some particular literary movement or grouping, or on some particular author.
Source:
Fédération Internationale des Langues et Littératures Modernes (International Federation for Modern Languages and Literatures)
Use Restriction
Permission to publish materials must be obtained in writing from the: New York University Archives, Elmer Holmes Bobst Library, 70 Washington Square South, New York, NY 10012, Phone: (212) 998-2646, Fax: (212) 995-4070, E-mail: university-archives@nyu.edu
Travel.; Administrative records.; Languages and languages.; Language and languages -- Study and teaching.; Language and languages -- Societies.; Photographs.; Correspondence.; Invitations.; Literature |x Societies, etc.; Minutes (administrative records); Budgets.; Grants.; Fundraising.; Syme, Ronald, 1903-1989; Baugh, Albert C. (Albert Croll), 1891-1981; Loeb Student Center; Modern Language Association of America; Modern Humanities Research Association; Pierpont Morgan Library; International Arthurian Society; Société de linguistique romane; Internationale Vereinigung für Germanische Sprach- und Literaturwissenschaft; Association internationale des études françaises; East-West Symposium; American Council of Learned Societies; Asia Foundation; Australasian Universities Modern Language and Literature Association; New York University; Cunard Steamship Company, ltd.
- Series I: General Files, 1959-1967; 1960-1964; 7 boxes
  - Addresses (9th International Congress of FILLM at NYU 1963), 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Asia Foundation, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ACIA (Literary History and Literary Criticism) of 9th International Congress of FILLM, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aston, Dr. Stanley (Correspondence) (1 of 6), 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aston, Dr. Stanley (Correspondence) (2 of 6), 1962 February-October (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aston, Dr. Stanley (Correspondence) (3 of 6), 1962 November-December (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Aston, Dr. Stanley (Correspondence) (4 of 6), 1963 January-June (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Aston, Dr. Stanley (Correspondence) (5 of 6), 1963 July-September (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Aston, Dr. Stanley (Correspondence) (6 of 6), 1963 October-December (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Australasian University Language and Literature Association, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Budget, N.Y.U. - For FILLM, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bureau Meeting: NYC, August 24, 27, 29, 1963, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bureau Meeting: July 1, 1963, 1961 April-July (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cunard Steamship Line (1 of 2), 1963 February-August (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cunard Steamship Line (2 of 2), 1963 August-1966 September (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - East-West Symposium (1 of 2), 1961 July-December (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - East-West Symposium (2 of 2), 1962 January-1964 July (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Emergency Chairmen, 1963 May (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - English: University Professors of, 1961 February-1962 October (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Etudes Francaises, 1960 November-1961 January (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Etudes Slaves, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fairfield Foundation: Luncheon, March 5, 1962, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Final Banquet, August 31, 1963, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Final Report: Stone, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Food Services: Monroe & Gal, 1963 June-September (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fugazy Travel Agency, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence (1 of 3), 1959 November-1962 October (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence (2 of 3), 1962 November-1963 August (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence (3 of 3), 1963 September-1967 December (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence: Important Letters, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hispanics, 1961 April-1962 December (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Hotels, Tours, Etc. (Correspondence), 1960 June-1963 June (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Hotels, Tours, Etc. (General), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Housing (1 of 2), 1961 June-1963 June (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Housing (2 of 2), 1963 June-September (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Hubell, Professor: List of Monies Received, 1963 February-December (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Insurance: Sickness and Accident, 1963 June-September (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Internationale Vereinigung Fur Germanische Sprach (1 of 2), 1960-1961 March (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Internationale Vereinigung Fur Germanische Sprach (2 of 2), 1963 August (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Invitations, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Invitations to Universities (1 of 2), 1961 July 24-25 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Invitations to Universities (2 of 2), 1961 July 31-November 14 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Invitations: Answers to-from Universities (1 of 2), 1961 July-1963 January (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Invitations: Answers to-from Universities (2 of 2), 1963 January-August (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Invited Scholars (1 of 2), 1962 November-1963 April (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Invited Scholars (2 of 2), 1963 May-June (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lam, Elizabeth (1 of 2), 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Lam, Elizabeth (2 of 2), 1963 January-July (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - LIEGE Meetings and Minutes (1 of 3), 1958-1960 October (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - LIEGE Meetings and Minutes (2 of 3), 1960 December-1961 November (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - LIEGE Meetings and Minutes (3 of 3), 1962 February-1963 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - LIEGE, Prior to the, 1959 January-1960 August (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - List of Contributors and Special Guests, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Litterature Comparee, 1960 November-1962 November (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Littauer Foundation, Inc., Mr. Harry Starr, 1963 April-December (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Loeb Student Center, 1963 May-September (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Luncheon: Dr. Stanley Aston and Professor Albert Baugh, January 10, 1963, 1963 January 4-10 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Luncheon: Mr. Jose de Cubas, Thursday March 20, 1962, 1962 March 14-20 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Luncheon: Mr. Arthur Houghton, President of the Corning Glass Co., April 19, 1962, 1964 March (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Luncheon: M.L.A., June 8, 1961; September 22, 1961; December 20, 1961, 1961 May-December (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Luncheon: National Advisory Committee, May 25, 1962, 1962 April-May (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Luncheon: Professor Saburo Ota, November 1, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Luncheon: Mr. David A. Shepard, Vice President of Standard Oil, April 3, 1962, 1962 April 3 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Luncheon: Mr. Starr, President & Treasurer of the Littauer Foundation, April 30, 1962, 1962 April 11-30 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Luncheon: Mr. Julian Street, Staff Director of Educational Services of ULSL Steel Foundation, April 9, 1962, 1962 March 27-April 17 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Luncheon: Sir Ronald Syme, November 9, 1962, 1962 October 29-November 9 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Luncheon: Mr. Paul Wollstadt, Vice President for PR Socony Mobil Oil Company, May 18, 1962, 1962 May 11-18 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Membership Lists, 1960 October-1962 July (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - MLA - Chicago Meeting, December 27-29, 1961, 1961 November-December (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - MLA - New York Meeting, December 27-29, 1964, 1964 December 27-29 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - MLA Meeting - Chicago, December 27, 1963, 1960 April-1962 May (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - MLA Meeting - Chicago, December 27, 1963, 1963 December 27 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Modern Humanities Research Association, 1960 December-1965 December (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Modern Language Association, 1961 February-1964 September (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - National Advisory Committee, 1961 January-1962 October (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - New York University Committee, 1959 June-1963 July (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Opening Session: Speakers, 1962 July-1963 August (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Pictures: Pan Am of Group Flight, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Pierpont-Morgan Library, 1963 June-August (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Post-Congress Letters of Appreciation, 1963 September-December (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Post-Congress Reports, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Presentation for Fund Raising, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Public Occasions, 1963 May-August (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Registration Fee: $12, 1962 July-1963 July (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Report to the FILLM Delegate, 1959 July-1960 December (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Requests for Check, 1962 March-1963 September (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Request for Programs, 1963 August 5-23 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Request Subsidiaries, 1961 April-1963 March (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Rotary International, 1961 August-June 1962 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Second Circulars: Questionnaires, 1962 February 15-26 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Societe Arthurienne, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Societe de Linguistique Romane, 1959-1961 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - State Department: Mr. Whitaker, 1963 February-July (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Stone, George Winchester, 1962 July-1965 March (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Strasbourg Congress, 1966, 1963 October-1966 September (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Studi Di Lingua E Litteratura Italiana, 1961 January-March (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Subsidiaries: Sources of for Travel Grants, 1961 May-1963 March (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Tours & Visits, 1962 July-1963 August (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Travel: Dean McKee, 1960 November-1964 January (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Travel Grant Invitations, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Travel Grant Recommendations from Member Associations, 1961 January-April (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Travel Negotiations, 1961 October-1963 May (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1961 June-1963 February (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Vanderbilt Hall, 1963 May-September (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Vitae Sheets, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Working Lists of Names, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)